Guide to the David Morris Potter Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
David Morris Potter papers
1942-1971
SC0088
Potter, David Morris
33.25 Linear feet
Professional papers.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Catherine M. Potter, 1971; Richard S. Barnes, 1973; Oxford University Press, 1973; Don E. Fehrenbacher, 1977, 1978, and 1989; Otis Pease, 1979; and George Knoles, 1979.
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Coe professor of history at Stanford (1961-1971); president of American Historical Association. Potter was born in 1910 and died in 1971.
Description of the Collection
Professional papers.
Scope and Contents note
Professional papers.
Access Terms
Fehrenbacher, Don Edward, 1920-1997.; Potter, David Morris; Stanford University. Department of History. Faculty.; Stanford University. Department of History. Students.; Stanford University. Department of History.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Professional correspondence, A-Z, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
  - Restricted Correspondence (Box 1A)
  - Potter - bibliography (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Placement correspondence (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Reference letters for students, -1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Rosters (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters of reference - students, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters of reference - defaulted (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Looking for positions (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters of reference, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters of reference 1969-70, non-grad students, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bird books - invoices, etc. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Potter - recent correspondence (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Professional correspondence A-Z, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Unfiled correspondence (Box 2)
  - Restricted material from box 2 (Box 2A)
  - Two folders of letters received while at Oxford University, with a few drafts of outgoing letters, 1947-48 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence A-Z 1956-1961 (incoming and some outgoing carbons) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Series of Potter's folders:Stephen Kline (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Series of Potter's folders: Correspondence: my teaching, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Series of Potter's folders: Letters answered, 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Series of Potter's folders: University College, London, 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Series of Potter's folders: Answered or not to be answered, 1942-1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Series of Potter's folders: Items not requiring an answer, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Series of Potter's folders: Correspondence answered (to be filed), 1948-1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Series of Potter's folders: Correspondence, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Series of Potter's folders: Council, AHA, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Series of Potter's folders: Humanities Foundation and Behavioral Center (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Series of Potter's folders: Program on Culture, OAH, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Accordion files of letters received A-Z, 1947-1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Accordion files of letters received A-Z, 1950-1956 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (Box 5)
  - Correspondence A-Z for, mostly letters received with a few carbons of outgoing letters and a few drafts of letters., 1932-1947 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Letters received from his parents (mostly his mother), 1933-1948 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, largely from family and friends, 1927-1937 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Two folders of correspondence to be filed, 1955-1960 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Teaching materials-Yale (Box 8)
  - Teaching materials-Stanford (Box 9)
  - Teaching materials-Stanford (Box 10)
  - Teaching materials, lecture notes, grade books, appointment books (Box 11)
  - Teaching materials-Stanford (Box 12)
  - Writings-Scott Foresman text (Box 13)
  - Research and bibliographical notes, letter record (Box 14)
  - Professional committees, etc (Box 15)
  - Album containing various articles (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Potter - book reviews and notes (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Saturday Review and the New Republic - assorted copies (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Saturday Review (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Saturday Review and Yale Review - assorted copies (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Assorted publications (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous lectures - notes and typescript (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Lecture at Stanford - written draft and correspondence, 1963 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Journalism conference at Stanford - program, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - American women - written and typed drafts (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Paper for Committee on Historical Analysis - written and typed drafts; notes; and correspondence (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Paper on Vice-Presidents - typescript (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Paper on advertising; originally for the Sat. Rev. (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Paper for Barnes Riznik - written and typed draft; notes; and correspondence, 1961-63, 1961-1963 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Article for Am. Hist. Review – multiple versions (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Paper on Nationalism - written and typed drafts (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Article on Nationalism - typescript, correspondence (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Lincoln and His Party" - written and typed drafts (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Trail to California, Revision - correspondence, notes, text re preface by Potter, 1948, 1961 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Hinton Helper - biographical note (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Paper for Yale Review, 50th year - mss and typescript (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Typed textbook script, chaps. 1-3 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - typed textbook script, chaps. 4-7 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Quest for the National Character - written and typed script, correspondence re publication, 1959-62, 1952-1962 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Phillips Introduction and Bibliography (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Abolition Movement - article for Encyc. Britt. (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Huey Pierce Long - article for Encyc. Britt. (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Papers for LS. U. Press (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Richard Watson - correspondence, 1959-1961 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - The South - article and notes, 1963 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Nathan Hale - notes, articles, and facsimile of Hale letter (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Walgreen lectures - typed text (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Walgreen lectures - notes (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - People of Plenty - typed article, and various publications re, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - American economics and agriculture (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Problems book - revisions requested by Henry Holt, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Problems - notes (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Disputes in coal industry - typescript articles (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - M. Savary letter with historical analysis, notes (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - Undergraduate papers (Box 17, Folder 22)
  - Elmer Henry - photographs and papers by Henry (Box 17, Folder 23)
  - Papers written by Potter in graduate school (Box 17, Folder 24)
  - Ralph Ross - article and Potter's response, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 25)
  - John Brown - written manuscript (Box 17, Folder 26)
  - Herman Belz paper - Reconstruction of the Union (Box 17, Folder 27)
  - Division and the Stresses - Chap 1 typescript and critique of material (Box 17, Folder 28)
  - Division and the Stresses - Chap. 1-3 typescript (Box 17, Folder 29)
  - Division and the Stresses - Chaps. 1-4 typescript (Box 17, Folder 30)
  - Review of Pacific Circle - printed and typescript versions (Box 17, Folder 31)
  - Review of Catton - printed version, notes, and correspondence re publication, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 32)
  - Potter, memo re Report of the History Panel (Box 17, Folder 33)
  - Review of Heard Round the World - typescript and correspondence, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 34)
  - Critique of Stampp paper (Box 17, Folder 35)
  - Division and the Stresses - notes (Box 17, Folder 36)
  - Women's Magazines and Woman's Role in American life" - first draft, correspondence with Good Housekeeping, 1955 "And Nixon Makes Eight" and "Heirs to the Presidency" - typescript and correspondence re publication (Box 17, Folder 37)
  - "American Leisure as an American Force" - written draft and correspondence re publication, 1963, 1968-1969 (Box 17, Folder 38)
  - L.S.U. - South and Sectional Conflict - correspondence with L.S.U. Press re his book, 1968-69 and correspondence 1963 with Alexander Riasanovsky re publication, 1963, 1968-1969 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - South and Sectional Conflict--reviews, publicity, 1969-1970 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - South and Sectional Conflict - corrections in mss for the galleys (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Bobb-Merrill - correspondence and financial records, 1969 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - My writing - manuscripts, typescripts, reprints of articles, reviews, speeches with some clippings and letters, 1952-1963 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Permissions - correspondence re use of Potter's work, 1967-1970 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - United States Information Service lincoln Exhibition - catalog for traveling exhibit; texts selected by Potter, Circa 1959 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - ROTC - my address - text and correspondence re talk at commissioning ceremony, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Review copy of The Progressive Historians by Richard Hofstadter; with Potter's comments [not foldered] (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - DMP-bibliography, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - list of Ph.D.'s completed with DMP (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Bobbs-Merrill - correspondence, bibliography re Reprint Series in American History, 1963-1966 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Kyoto - phone memo (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Class Day Talk - text of talk on class day at Stanford, 1967 Jun 17 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Genovese Paper - correspondence, text re Potter's comments on Eugene Genovese's paper on U.B. Phillips and its publication, 1966-1977 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - AHA Dec '68 Stampp Paper - correspondence re Potter as commentator, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Reviews - correspondence, text, 1965-1966, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Review of Status Politics - correspondence, text, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Journalism Prog - background info on conference where Potter spoke, 1968 Jun 26 (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - Essay for [C. Vann] Woodward on Civil War - broadcast lecture on Voice of America, correspondence and text, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - Conference Danforth Fellows - correspondence, 1968 Feb 6-9 (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - Commission on Violence [National Commission on the Causes and Prevention of Violence] - correspondence, text of comments, information, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - PCB meeting Aug. 1968 [Pacific Coast Branch of AHA] - correspondence, text of talks by others, 1968 August (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - Planting Fields- correspondence, lists, bibliography, lecture notes from Potter's course at Institute for American History and Government at SUNY, Stony Brook, 1966 Summer (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - Conf. on Political Parties-St. Louis - summary report (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - [Daniel J.] Boorstin Anthology - correspondence and text for Potter's entry to Boors tin 's American Primer, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - Canada-U.S. - correspondence and text for Potter's article in Canada Views the United States, 1966-67, 1966-1967 (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - Janeway [Eliot] - correspondence and publications by Janeway, 1967 (Box 18, Folder 28)
  - Paper at Duke - correspondence, galleys, text re participation in symposium and publication of paper, 1966-67, 1966-1967 (Box 18, Folder 29)
  - Pickett papers - mss copies of historical sources (Box 18, Folder 30)
  - Civil Rights- clippings and articles, 1966 Summer (Box 18, Folder 31)
  - Southern Sectionalism - research correspondence, notes, clippings, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 32)
  - Senior Class Day - correspondence and text of talk, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 33)
  - St. John Papers - info re Isaac Munroe St. John Papers at Yale University library, 1951 (Box 18, Folder 34)
  - Symposium on People of Plenty at San Francisco - correspondence and text of comment, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 35)
  - Civil War pictures - photographs and negatives of illustrations (Box 18, Folder 36)
  - Anderson at Sumter - notes from contemporary sources (Box 18, Folder 37)
  - Detweiler Paper - correspondence and text of review for Journal of Southern History, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 38)
  - Mississippi: maps, legis. apportionment - research notes (Box 18, Folder 39)
  - Carbon copies-Phillips notes - typescripts of historical sources of 1850s (Box 18, Folder 40)
  - Henry Adams and Boston Advertiser - typescript copies of sources; typescript article by Potter; manuscript notes (Box 18, Folder 41)
  - Reprints by others (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Broadcasts at Texas - correspondence, notes re 1V lectures, 1962-1963 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Misc. U.S. lectures - notes (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Bobbs-Merrill Reprint Series in American History - correspondence, lists, catalog, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Bobbs-Merrill - correspondence, catalogs, lists, 1963-1964 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Hexter manuscript - on historiography, with one page of comments by Potter, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous - clipping re students being ignorant of U.S. history, 1943 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Yale Press-Janeway [Eliot] - correspondence of Potter, Janeway, George Pannly Day of Yale Press, and Arthur H. Brook re mss of Janeway's, 1950-51, 1950-1951 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Comparative Civilization - seminar papers, Center for Advanced Study in Behavioral Sciences, 1958 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Janeway - correspondence, 1950-59, with some clippings and reviews, 1950-1959 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Ronald Press - correspondence re mss Potter reviewed with some notes, 1944-1950 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Advertising - examples and notes for proposed article, and correspondence, 1958 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Herzenberg [Leonard A.] - correspondence re rejection of Potter's daughter from summer program at Stanford Medical School, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Program at SHA 1966 on Confederate leaders after the War - correspondence and one paper (Potter was chair of session) (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - untitled - articles on Civil Rights, 1958-1963 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - First Sumter Centennial - clippings, 1961 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - History of the South - bibliography, exam questions, assignments, clippings plus an 1895 brochure re lecture tour of Gen. John B. Gordon (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Negro - one clipping, 1967-1968 (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - History of South - clippings, articles, notes, bibliography, 1947-1960 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - South- clippings, notes, reprints, bibliography, 1961-1964 (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - South - clippings re Democratic Convention, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - untitled - misc. clippings, bibliographies, sources (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - Segregation-Citizens' Council Material- publications and brochures by CC and newspapers from other segregationist organizations, 1959-63, 1959-1963 (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - Oxford, Miss Riots 1966 - clippings (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Potter, Memorandum on the Report of the History Panel, Behavioral and Social Sciences Survey, May 1969 (2 copies) (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - Potter, Historical Aspects of the Rejection of or Disaffiliation from the Prevaling American Society, n.d. (2 copies) (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - Typescript paper "The Virginia Council" by Leonard W. Labaree with extensive genealogy charts, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Note cards for lecture "Three Woodrow Wilsons" during Berkeley summer session, 1965 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Professional correspondence A-H, 1950s (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Professional correspondence I-Z, 1950s (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Professional correspondence, 1960s (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - [Chapter XIV; South and Sectional Conflict lectures; placement correspondence Sept. 69-70; Furness lectures - conflict/consensus; Dilys; loose notes; Fleming lectures;], 1969-1970 (Box 24)
  - [Southern history essays; loose papers; Committee on the Hoover; misc; OAH since Nov. 1970; OAH April 70 meeting; OAH committees], Since 1970 (Box 25)
  - [OAH since 4/70; placement 1970; Molly Minehan; OAH Committees before April 1970; Snyder; DP correspondence; Departmental; Bernstein; Bernstein-archive] (Box 26)
  - Letters of reference to be filed (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Answer - personal (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Later action (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - No title (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Defer (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - No title - correspondence, 1969 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - No title - correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence to be filed (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Misc. correspondence (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Misc. notes (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript copies of papers and lectures. Also, holograph MS of The South and the Concurrent Majority, published 1972; the Fleming lectures were delivered from this MS. (Box 28)
  - First draft, holograph, of Potter's 2-vol. book for Harpers on the Coming of the Civil War, chapters 1-9. (Box 29)
  - First draft, holograph, of Potter's 2-vol. book for Harpers on the Coming of the Civil War, chapters 10-19 (incomplete). (Box 30)
  - Unfinished MSS of textbook on American history (1953-56). Chapters I-VI holograph with Potter's corrections; correspondence with the typist Katherine Barnes. Copy of John E. Cook's The Wearing of the Grey, with three letters from Cook., 1953-1956 (Box 31)
  - Annotated MSS of History and AmeriCan Society, chapters 1-16 and index (Box 32)
  - Galley proofs of History and American Society; reviews of The South and the Concurrent Majority (Box 33)
  - MSS of Freedom and Its Limitations on American Life; review of Craven's Historian and the Ciyil War (Box 34)
  - Publishers MSS of The Impending Crisis (Box 35)
  - Publishers MSS of The Impending Crisis (Box 36)
  - Paper by Walter Metzger and comments, Circa 1960 (Box 37)
  - J.K. Galbraith's The Affluent Society, annotated by Potter for reviewing (Box 38)